<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Hydro@UMass</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/</link><atom:link href="https://hydro-umass.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Hydro@UMass</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://hydro-umass.github.io/media/icon_hu7bf4dc0a2f2b0b6f2de776cdc877e948_11369_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Hydro@UMass</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/</link></image><item><title>Deploying JupyterHub on the Cloud</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/post/jupyter-hub/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 16:35:29 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/post/jupyter-hub/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m teaching a class on computational methods for environmental engineers this
semester, and the language of choice is Python as it is simple enough for
potentially novice programmers and has a very rich ecosystem of existing
libraries that make life easier for any environmental engineer/scientist. As I
have taught the class once before, I emphasized reproducibility which meant that
we used Jupyter notebooks for most of the class. The other aspect of the class
that I found tremendously useful was live coding. Thankfully, the &lt;a href="https://github.com/damianavila/RISE" target="_blank" rel="noopener">RISE extension&lt;/a>
combines Jupyter notebooks with slideshows (powered by &lt;a href="https://revealjs.com/#/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Reveal.js&lt;/a> presentation
framework) and I ended up using it exclusively for preparing the lectures.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Although a good chunk of the class was spent with the students coding on their
own with me going around answering questions, I decided to take it a step
further by utilizing a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flipped%5Fclassroom" target="_blank" rel="noopener">flipped classroom&lt;/a> approach and combining it with
paired/grouped learning. Essentially the students go over some lecture material
prior to class, and we spend most of the lecture time explaining anything
that the students had trouble but leave enough time for groups of students to
solve a coding problem (relevant to the lecture material of course). The last
part of the lecture is spent going over the answers of each student group and
answering any questions. This presents a technology issue: it would be too much
of a hassle to connect each student&amp;rsquo;s laptop to the projector in order to show
their answers to the entire class. The answer would be to set up a server where
the students can connect and solve the problem in Jupyter notebooks on the
server. &lt;a href="https://jupyter.org/hub" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jupyter Hub&lt;/a> would be the solution, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to have all the
students connect to my laptop.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here&amp;rsquo;s where the &lt;a href="https://github.com/jupyterhub/the-littlest-jupyterhub" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the Littlest JupyterHub (TLJH)&lt;/a> comes in, which is a
distribution that helps you provide Jupyter Notebooks to 1-50 users on a single
server (hosted on a cloud provider potentially). In this post, I will document
how I set up TLJH on the Google Cloud.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first step involves logging in to the &lt;a href="https://console.cloud.google.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Google Cloud Console&lt;/a> and creating a
new VM instance. You can keep the default options except for:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Change the Boot Disk image from &lt;code>Debian GNU/Linux 9 (Stretch)&lt;/code> to &lt;code>Ubuntu 18.04 LTS&lt;/code>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Disable any service accounts (under &lt;code>Identity and API access&lt;/code>)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Check the &lt;strong>Allow HTTP Traffic&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>Allow HTTPS Traffic&lt;/strong> checkboxes under &lt;code>Firewall&lt;/code>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Customize the &lt;code>Startup script&lt;/code> under &lt;code>Management, disks, networking, SSH keys&lt;/code>
with the following&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-sh" data-lang="sh">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="c1">#!/bin/bash&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> curl https://raw.githubusercontent.com/jupyterhub/the-littlest-jupyterhub/master/bootstrap/bootstrap.py &lt;span class="se">\
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="se">&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">|&lt;/span> sudo python3 - &lt;span class="se">\
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="se">&lt;/span> --admin &amp;lt;admin-user-name&amp;gt;
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>After creating the VM and waiting a few minutes for TLJH to be installed, grab
the external IP of your VM (without the ~ &lt;a href="https://" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://&lt;/a> ~ part) and login to your new
server. If you click on the &lt;code>Control Panel&lt;/code> and the &lt;code>Admin&lt;/code> link, you can add
users (i.e. your students). Now we can have prepared Jupyter notebooks on the
cloud, that each student can work on and go over the problems/answers from a
single machine!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Evaluating Peak Discharge and Urbanization Impacts with Random Forest Regression</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/kim2023/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/kim2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>A multi-sensor approach to characterize winter water level drawdown patterns in lakes</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/kumar2023/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/kumar2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>ResORR: A Globally Scalable and Satellite Data-driven Algorithm for River Flow Regulation due to Reservoir Operations</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/das2023/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/das2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Developing a stochastic hydrological model for informing lake water level drawdown management</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/he2023/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/he2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Dryspells and Minimum Air Temperatures Influence Rice Yield and its Forecasts in Rainfed Systems</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/abhishek2023/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/abhishek2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Low-Flow (7-Day, 10-Year) Classical Statistical and Improved Machine Learning Estimation Methodologies</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/delsanto2023/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/delsanto2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Satellite-based Tracking of Reservoir Operations for Flood Management during the 2018 Extreme Weather Event in Kerala, India</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/suresh2023/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/suresh2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Evaluation of a regional crop model implementation for sub-national yield assessments in Kenya</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/ellenburg2023/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/ellenburg2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Reservoir Assessment Tool Version 3.0: A Scalable and User-Friendly Software Platform to Mobilize the Global Water Management Community</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/minocha2023/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/minocha2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Forecasting Summer Water Demand Using Optimized Random Forests: A Case Study of 12 US Utilities</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/bhuiyan2023/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/bhuiyan2023/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Assessing the impact of Sentinel-1 derived planting dates on rice crop yield modeling</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/hashemi2022/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/hashemi2022/</guid><description/></item><item><title>A data-driven framework to inform projections of aquatic flows in the Northeast</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/project/foaf/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/project/foaf/</guid><description>&lt;p>As climate change is impacting the future of aquatic flows, there is a great need for natural resource managers to assess adaptation measures in a holistic manner. The latter requires integrating multiple models with observational data, but that can be problematic due to disparities in terms of scale or fidelity of each model. Scientific machine learning, which has exploded in popularity in recent years, could provide a novel and flexible way of fusing observations and models. This project aims to develop a data-driven modeling framework that can help stakeholders incorporate the impacts of climate change into future predictions of aquatic flows. The proposed team will convene a working group composed of local, state and federal resource managers who are responsible for mitigating the impacts of climate change caused by extreme hydrologic events on fish and wildlife. Informed by this working group, the researchers will develop the data-driven framework by adopting modern computational methods that facilitate communication and ensure that the actual users of this framework are involved with its development from the ground up. The focus area of the proposed research will be the Northeast US, although the modeling tool is robust and can be applied within any region of the United States. Detailed user documentation and a simple interface will allow resource managers to incorporate the modeling tool into their existing workflow, making its adoption more likely. Data volumes are not getting any smaller, with more observations and model output becoming available to everyone. The overarching goal of this research is to bring in the very promising area of scientific maching learning into the hands of interested users and resource managers, ensuring fair access to such tools and demonstrating a different paradigm for climate change science.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Urbanizing the floodplain: Global changes of imperviousness in flood-prone areas</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/andreadis2022b/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/andreadis2022b/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Evaluation of Multi-scale SMAP Soil Moisture Products in Forested Environments</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/andreadis2022a/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/andreadis2022a/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Applications of remote sensing techniques to hydrologic research in Sub-Saharan Africa, with a special focus on the Congo basin</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/schumann2022/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/schumann2022/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Review of GPM IMERG performance: A global perspective</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/pradhan2021/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/pradhan2021/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Screening Tool for Dam Hazard Potential Classification Using Machine Learning and Multi-Objective Hyperparameter Tuning</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/kravits2021/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/kravits2021/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Probabilistic Evaluation of Drought in CMIP6 Simulations</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/papalexiou2021/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/papalexiou2021/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Evaluating the impacts of drought on rice productivity over Cambodia in the Lower Mekong Basin</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/abhishek2021/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/abhishek2021/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Exploring the factors controlling the performance of the Surface Water and Ocean Topography mission discharge algorithms</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/frasson2021/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/frasson2021/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Combining big-data remote sensing and global hydrologic modelling improves daily discharge estimates across an entire large watershed</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/ishitsuka2020/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/ishitsuka2020/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Constraining the assimilation of SWOT observations with hydraulic geometry relations</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/andreadis2020/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/andreadis2020/</guid><description/></item><item><title>A Data Assimilation Framework for Generating Space‐Time Continuous Daily SWOT River Discharge Data Products</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/li2020/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/li2020/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Underlying Fundamentals of Kalman Filtering for River Network Modeling</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/emery2020/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/emery2020/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Hello world!</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/post/hello-world/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2020 21:46:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/post/hello-world/</guid><description>&lt;p>Every blog starts with one of these. Right?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Developing a global assimilation and modeling framework to produce SWOT data products</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/project/swot/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/project/swot/</guid><description>&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://swot.jpl.nasa.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">SWOT satellite mission&lt;/a> will observe water surface elevation, slope, storage change (directly) and river discharge (indirectly) globally at unprecedented spatial resolutions and accuracies, potentially having a “transformational impact in terrestrial hydrology”. Although the SWOT data products of the aforementioned variables will be tremendously valuable they can be enhanced by combining with hydrologic and hydrodynamic models. In fact, there have been a few studies that have examined the value of assimilating SWOT observations into hydrodynamic models to estimate river discharge or channel bathymetry. The primary advantage of using a data assimilation approach is the estimation of continuous fields of the SWOT-observed variables in both space and time. Moreover, data assimilation can be used to infer other variables (e.g. runoff) or optimize model parameters by accounting for model and observation errors. With this project we are developing a modeling and assimilation framework specifically for SWOT observations that could be used to generate Level 4 data products.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Evaluation and diagnosis of the National Water Model snow simulations</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/project/nwm/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/project/nwm/</guid><description>&lt;p>Snow accumulation and its melt dominate water resources in mountainous areas, with regions such as the western United States deriving more than 75% of the total freshwater available annually from snowmelt. Rain-on-snow floods, in some cases amplified by frozen soils, have been responsible for some of the largest recorded floods in the West, as well as the North Central
States and the Northeast. Despite their importance snowpacks remain poorly quantified (especially, but not only, in topographically complex regions), leaving hydrological models such as the &lt;a href="https://water.noaa.gov/about/nwm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">National Water Model&lt;/a> (NWM) poorly constrained with significant uncertainty in both their physical and statistical parameterizations. Remote sensing can alleviate some of these limitations and recently-produced datasets from optical satellite sensors have provided long-term and high-resolution maps of snow water equivalent (SWE). In this project, we will extend a satellite-derived SWE reanalysis (from Landsat, MODIS, and VIIRS) over the Continental United States (CONUS) and assess the representation of SWE in the NWM. Apart from directly evaluating the output of the NWM in terms of SWE, we will diagnose model errors and characterize them both statistically as well as in terms of the model parameterizations. The results from the diagnostic and sensitivity analyses will be used to derive error models and improved parameterizations for NWM that will be tested and compared with the baseline NWM version.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Monitoring and forecasting drought and crop yield for the Lower Mekong Basin</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/project/servir/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/project/servir/</guid><description>&lt;p>Rice is Asia’s most important food crop with nearly 3 billion people reliant on rice as their major food source. Over the next ten years this number is expected to climb to nearly 4 billion people. Throughout Southeast Asia, the most important constraint to rice production is water stress, which affects nearly 10 million ha of upland rice and over 13 million ha of rain-fed lowland rice. Future climate change effects on rainfall timing and amount, and projected increases in temperature are expected to exacerbate existing water stresses and will have a direct impact on agriculture, especially rice cultivation. In a project funded by NASA and USAID through the &lt;a href="https://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/servir/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">SERVIR program&lt;/a>, we are providing the SERVIR-Mekong hub with the modeling and data system tools needed to produce linked hydrologic and crop yield as nowcasts, forecasts and at climate scales using the best available data including NASA Earth observations. The effort aims to “improve, enrich, and expand the use of Earth observations” to help make informed decisions in order to adapt to and reduce vulnerabilities from impacts of extreme events and future climate change in the Lower Mekong.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title> Improving Hydrologic Modeling Using Cloud-Free MODIS Flood Maps</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/tran2019/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/tran2019/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Role of Rain‐on‐Snow in Flooding Over the Conterminous United States</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/li2019b/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/li2019b/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Model-data fusion of hydrologic simulations and GRACE terrestrial water storage observations to estimate changes in water table depth</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/stampoulis2019/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/stampoulis2019/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Utility of Infrequent Snow Depth Images for Deriving Continuous Space‐Time Estimates of Seasonal Snow Water Equivalent</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/margulis2019/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/margulis2019/</guid><description/></item><item><title>The Value of Accurate High-Resolution and Spatially Continuous Snow Information to Streamflow Forecasts</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/li2019a/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/li2019a/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Rapid Mapping of Small-Scale River-Floodplain Environments Using UAV SfM Supports Classical Theory</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/schumann2019/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/schumann2019/</guid><description/></item><item><title>A High-Resolution Data Assimilation Framework for Snow Water EquivalentEstimation across the Western United States and Validation with theAirborne Snow Observatory</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/oaida2019/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/publication/oaida2019/</guid><description/></item><item><title/><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/contact/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/contact/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Lake ecosystems</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/project/lakes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/project/lakes/</guid><description>&lt;p>Human acceleration of eutrophication through continued watershed and lakeshore development, combined with changes in temperature and climate, increasingly challenges managers to meet human needs while protecting aquatic resources. While annual winter water level drawdowns (WDs) are commonly used to reduce nuisance macrophyte biomass, the future utility and impacts to ecosystems under climate change remains uncertain. Moreover, the timing and magnitude of drawdowns, which are affected by climate, influences the negative impacts of drawdowns on lake water quality and food webs. Using remote sensing data, validated with on-the-ground water level and cyanobacteria data, we will characterize water level fluctuations and cyanobacteria blooms in WD lakes coupled to novel hydrologic models that assess sensitivity of these lakes to future climate and precipitation. The results from this research, which will be shared in scientific publications, will help evaluate WDs as a macrophyte management tool under future climate change and weigh any remaining benefits with the ecological and socioeconomic costs of performing WDs. This research is a collaboration between the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), University of Massachusetts Amherst, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, and seven state agencies, who will provide in-kind support for collection of field data and translate results into guidance for lake managers.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Urbanization and flooding</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/project/flooding/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/project/flooding/</guid><description>&lt;p>Floods are one of the costliest natural disasters both in terms of
damages and human livelihood losses. Urban encroachment on
floodplains increases exposure and vulnerability to floods while
population changes and climate change are expected to exacerbate
those risks. Although
the mechanisms of how urbanization affects flood risk are relatively
well understood, there have been limited efforts in assessing the
degree of floodplain encroachment globally and how it has changed
both in space and time. With the advent of big-data geospatial
processing tools, global-scale reconstructions of flood risk and
changes in urban area have been made available and by combining
these datasets, we can assess how floodplains have urbanized in
relation to flood risk globally.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>