<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Modeling | Hydro@UMass</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/tag/modeling/</link><atom:link href="https://hydro-umass.github.io/tag/modeling/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Modeling</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://hydro-umass.github.io/media/icon_hu7bf4dc0a2f2b0b6f2de776cdc877e948_11369_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Modeling</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/tag/modeling/</link></image><item><title>Urbanization and flooding</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/projects/flood-urbanization/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/projects/flood-urbanization/</guid><description>&lt;p>Floods are one of the costliest natural disasters both in terms of damages and human livelihood losses. Urban encroachment on floodplains increases exposure and vulnerability to floods while population changes and climate change are expected to exacerbate those risks. Although the mechanisms of how urbanization affects flood risk are relatively well understood, there have been limited efforts in assessing the degree of floodplain encroachment globally and how it has changed both in space and time. With the advent of big-data geospatial processing tools, global-scale reconstructions of flood risk and changes in urban area have been made available and by combining these datasets, we can assess how floodplains have urbanized in relation to flood risk globally.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Lake ecosystems</title><link>https://hydro-umass.github.io/projects/lakes/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hydro-umass.github.io/projects/lakes/</guid><description>&lt;p>Human acceleration of eutrophication through continued watershed and lakeshore development, combined with changes in temperature and climate, increasingly challenges managers to meet human needs while protecting aquatic resources. While annual winter water level drawdowns (WDs) are commonly used to reduce nuisance macrophyte biomass, the future utility and impacts to ecosystems under climate change remains uncertain. Moreover, the timing and magnitude of drawdowns, which are affected by climate, influences the negative impacts of drawdowns on lake water quality and food webs. Using remote sensing data, validated with on-the-ground water level and cyanobacteria data, we will characterize water level fluctuations and cyanobacteria blooms in WD lakes coupled to novel hydrologic models that assess sensitivity of these lakes to future climate and precipitation. The results from this research, which will be shared in scientific publications, will help evaluate WDs as a macrophyte management tool under future climate change and weigh any remaining benefits with the ecological and socioeconomic costs of performing WDs. This research is a collaboration between the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), University of Massachusetts Amherst, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, and seven state agencies, who will provide in-kind support for collection of field data and translate results into guidance for lake managers.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>